[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
e-r. se radio is brought to you by the
it computer society and by It software
Magazine online at computer.org
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert bluman today I have with
me William Morgan William is the CEO of
buyant and one of the cre ERS of linkerd
William has been active on
k753 which is called sidecar containers
for
kubernetes and that's what we will be
talking about William would you like to
add anything to your background that I
didn't cover uh well yeah first of all
thanks for having me Robert it's great
to be here I think calling me active on
the K is very charitable I've been a
cheerleader for it and you know I wrote
a blog post about it because it kind of
impacted did a lot of what we did in
Linker D land but beyond that my
background really has been very heavily
focused on sidecars and service meshes
and kubernetes and all that stuff so
yeah that's probably the only thing I'd
really want to add that all sounds great
and we will be talking about many of
those things today we often do some
background in episodes but we've done a
lot of content recently on kubernetes so
we're going to assume listeners know
some Basics there we have you our
archives episode 446 on kubernetes
fundamentals and 590 on standing up
kubernetes we did also cover service
mesh and side cars a while ago in 361 I
would like to review that a bit first
can you explain what is a
sidecar yeah so sidecar is the name for
a pattern effectively and and when we
talk about the meat of the episode and
the K what's interesting about the K is
that for the first time it actually
there's a side car object in kubernetes
but up until now it's just been the name
for a pattern which is if you kind of
visualize a sidecar next to a motorcycle
your motorcycles your application
container and we're adding a container
next to that and what the container does
kind of is up to whoever the contents of
the container but the pattern is really
hey you've got your main application
container and we're adding this thing
next to it very simple right but it
turns out that that pattern opens up a
lot of really interesting opportunities
in a system like kubernetes which makes
it very easy to do because it kind of
allows this form of dynamic binding
right where because these things are
containers they could be written in
different languages they can be written
by different teams but they can kind of
work together in a sense and they get
scheduled together they live and die
together but yeah ultimately it's just
the name for this pattern where you have
a side container stuck onto your main
application container we will be talking
a bit about service mesh so we'll have
plenty of examples there can you give an
example of a sidecar use case other than
service mesh yeah I think a common one
is for logging infrastructure or maybe
even monitoring infrastructure where you
have some agent that's sitting in the
side car that's poking at the
application container and Reporting
metrics or reporting log messages back
to some centralized service so that way
you offload that functionality from the
application you still get to run it kind
of as if it were part of the application
I became aware of side cars in relation
to service mesh is there a history of
cars before service mesh or were they
invented
primarily alongside service mesh in the
context of kubernetes yeah probably
those two things came about at more or
less the same time certainly the idea of
running something next to something else
is not like a novel idea for for
kubernetes or for anything but yeah I
think historically they they emerged at
just about the same time and I think if
you look back through the very early
kubernetes docks the first mention or
two of Sidecar ours was 2015 2016 just
about the early days of when service
measures were coming to to your you
referred to the main container and the
side car but my understanding is service
V predates kubernetes is this inherently
a container orchestration pattern or
could it be any two binaries that are
running on the same host and working
together yeah that's a great question
and I'm fortunate or maybe unfortunate
enough to have had a seat right in the
kind of the creation phase of this so
the project I work on is Linker d l i n
ke Rd and kind of the origins you know I
kind of mentioned Dynamic Bing the
origin to that name where we were
thinking about an operating system and
there's a Linker in an operating system
which kind of does this runtime Dynamic
binding of a application in a library
that it relies on and then we put a d at
the end because in Unix terminology
right that's like the demon so now we
have this thing that looks like it's
pronounced like something else but it's
pronounced Linker and as that name might
Bell the origins of this were prior to
kubernetes in fact my co-founder Oliver
and I came out of the world of maos we
we were engineers at Twitter and we had
cut our teeth on these large scale maos
deployments so the original version of
linerty which was the very first service
mesh and was a project that even coined
the term service mesh you know the
origins of that was didn't have anything
to do with kubernetes or even containers
it was like Hey we've got this amazing
Library you know that all these
interesting things but it's like a Scala
library that doesn't help anyone except
for you know Scala programmers or at
least people who are running on the jvm
so what if we package that thing up as a
proxy and we kind of like stick it next
to your application in the very first
use cases didn't have anything to do
with sidecars or containers or
kubernetes that project Linker became
very popular kind of right around the
time where kubernetes was becoming very
popular so we kind of and there's a long
history there we ended up rewriting
everything and like making it very
kubernetes specific but yeah absolutely
the original idea had nothing to do with
with sidecars but everything to do with
kind of being a partner to the
application so not being a library that
the developers would have to do
something with but being something that
you can add at runtime where the
platform team or the Ops Team or devops
team was the one who kind of owned that
functionality versus the developers
owning that functionality you
consciously decided not then to try TR
to link your Linker Library into the
same binary as the main application it
would be in this side car how did the
main application and the side car
communicate with each other yeah so
that's the trick it's like okay now
you've got these two arbitrary pieces of
code and they have to somehow talk to
each other and so we turn to the
patterns laid down by our ancestors and
the Unix networking stack so we said
okay this thing is going to act as a
proxy and you're going to make all of
your calls through the proxy and in fact
the very early versions of this we
literally use the HTTP proxy like
environment variable which most programs
respect kind of got wired through
everything in the late 90s or maybe mid
2000s and so you could say hey I'm going
through a proxy and you would point it
to like the linkerd proxy and all your
calls would go through there and the
linkerd proxy would basically intercept
those things do stuff in quotes you know
and then when the response came back go
back to your your application so you
know technically is acting both as a
proxy and as a reverse proxy that was
really the only trick there was you can
use a network and that is the way that
these two things communicate now you
know is a network the best way I don't
know you know you can get optimizations
if you look at Unix domain sockets you
can do fancy stuff these days with
things like ebpf but you know ultimately
if you look at where the latency where
the cost lies all of those things don't
make a huge difference compared to what
your application is doing so yeah we
still to this day end up just using
literally running IP tables to like wire
up the network calls to go through the
proxy in this original implementation
was the proxy in user mode or kernel
mode all user mode even the modern
implementations it's all user mode I'm
not a fan of doing anything in the
kernel unless you really have to okay
could you say a bit more about that why
do you think that well you know partly
this is philosophical which is the
kernel is where scary things happen
right that's where you have unlimited
access to everything so why would we put
ourselves in that path if we can avoid
it and then partly is well we haven't
really needed to ebpf now kind of blurs
the line and that's probably worth the
whole podcast in of itself but even in
ebpf mode you know the way you're
interacting with the colel is in this
very limited very restrictive way so
unless there's a really compelling
reason for you to enter into those
Waters which I think in the vast
majority of cases there aren't just do
this all in user mode the arguments
usually for getting into the konel our
performance arguments hey we need to be
faster hey we need to be as fast as
possible but again in the context of a
modern distributed system application
running in containers on kubernetes on a
VM and the cloud the source of latency
is not these little Network calls it's
not in the CIS call boundary between
user space and and the kernel the source
of latency is like your application
talking to the database which sits in
some other Zone over there we do have
some content on ebpf I'll be sure to put
that in the show notes I've got a lot of
opinions too so you know if you really
want to get into this I'm happy to and I
wrote a blog post about ebpf and
sidecars too because that's an
interesting debate kind of in the
service mesh World which is like is ebpf
so incredible so amazing that we can get
rid of sidecars you know and there's
like marketing that suggests you can and
then when you dig into it engineering
that suggests you cannot we'll see how
much time we have if we get into that a
bit later for now I want to switch we've
been talking about sidecars generally to
more about service mess which has come
up a few times but haven't asked you
directly what it is yeah so I think
there's two basic ways of looking at it
there's kind of the application way and
and there's a network way and I'll start
with the application way because that's
kind of my background so the goal of a
service mesh is to give you a bunch of
features without having to bother the
developers so you in this case is the
platform team the devops folks whoever
is responsible for running this
kubernetes uh you know based system and
we almost always talk about it in the
context of kubernetes not because
kubernetes is good or right or beautiful
or anything other than an eventuality
that we all have to accept at this point
but because that's kind of where these
two things grew up together and in
practice kubernetes gives us a bunch of
Primitives that we make heavy use of in
serit mesland but the idea is hey
kubernetes kind of acts as this building
block and on top of that we want to give
you a set of functionality right and we
want to do it in a way that the platform
team kind of owns this and what is that
functionality well it comes down to a
bunch of things that fall into kind of
three buckets security reliability and
observability so we have a set of
features in a service mesh around
security that are things like Mutual TLS
things like authorization policy you
know we call L7 authorization policy so
being able to accept or deny requests
from other
services in your application based on
specific routes or specific methods or
whatever that they're calling that's the
security bucket the reliability bucket
is things like request retries request
load balancing circuit breaking timeouts
failover things like that and then the
observability bucket typically comes
down to providing golden metrics for the
application so providing things like
success rates or failure rates latency
histograms and things like that and so
these are all things that you need I
think that are basically critical I
think for running an application at
scale and so your choice you know when
you're deploying your application is
like well either we have the developers
do that or we have the platform itself
do it and you know I think the power of
the service mesh is that a it can be
done at the platform so developers don't
have to implement TLS which they'll be
happy for and B when you do it that way
it's uniform across your application so
doesn't matter which team wrote this
service or what language it's in or
whatever everyone's reporting their HTTP
success rates in the exact same way
everyone's reporting their request
latency in the exact same way and that's
really powerful especially at scale so
that's kind of the application view the
networking view which is also
interesting to consider I think is like
hey this is basically a glorified new
network you know it's a new type of
network where kind of the Baseline
requirement you know in the olden days
the Baseline requirement of a network
was hey I've got to get my TCP packets
from point or my IP packets from point8
to point B right and if you can do that
then Network's done its job and if you
can't then like Network's broken right
and kind of in this new model you can
say well the job of the the service mesh
is to kind of elevate that to the world
of requests and so that every time I'm
making a request from application
component a to application component B
not only does that get delivered but it
gets delivered in a reliable way that's
able to handle failures of application
failures of network failures of whatever
in a way that's secure so that
connection gets encrypted and
authenticated so I have you know
confidentiality and authenticity and I'm
forgetting the third principle now
Integrity by default and you know and
it's observable right so we're
upleveling our Network so we have those
three characteristics in either way of
looking at it I think that's that's kind
of what the service m is at the at the
feature level and then when we get to
how it's implemented that's when we it's
only then when we get into like side
cars and ebpf and you know whatever the
hell else with kubernetes you have the
for kubernetes which has a number of
extension points and then there's a huge
ecosystem of add-ons that either run as
a service inside kubernetes or they
insert themselves within kind of a
extension point where they get then
incorporated into kubernetes troll plane
logic so to what extent is service mesh
is it a competitor to other attempts to
solve the same problem problems in the
kubernetes ecosystem or is it still
something that's completely got its own
domain where there isn't really an
alternative yeah there definitely are
multiple competing surface mesh projects
but does it compete with anything else
maybe the closest would be something
like gnats or rabbit mq or kind of like
a Qing system because one of the kind of
fundamental assumptions of the S well
more or less fundamental Assumption of
the service mesh is that'll your traffic
is synchronous HTTP or grpc calls and
that's where the service meas is most
valuable now there's like a
philosophical argument of which is
better and you know maybe message
passing is better and I've got my
opinions but leaving aside those
opinions when we talk about things like
retries and timeouts and circuit
breaking and latency histograms like
those are all really Centric to http
synchronous htttp calls all of the
really cool interesting features of
linkerd
most of them are centered on that but
beyond that I'd say that's kind of the
competitive landscape as I understand it
one thing I'm thinking of is in
kubernetes there's support for what's
called a network policy where you can
control who's able to talk to who which
sounds a lot like a feature of service
mesh do you have a take on that that's a
great point so with something like
Network policy which is available out of
the box on kubernetes it even ships with
it you can set things like Network
policies the boundary where those things
stop is that they stop at you know in
network terms at at layer four so you're
able to express things in terms of
service names which map to IP addresses
but you can't go beyond that so you
can't go to the level of individual HTP
methods or you know HTP routes or or
grpc methods you can't really do things
in terms of external host names or
anything that requires interpreting an
HTTP call in order to speak HTTP you
basically need to have a proxy so that's
where that boundary lies so we often
have people using linkerd and network
policies in conjunction where you kind
of set a set of Baseline things at layer
four with your network policy and then
when you get into the really fine
grained stuff that's where you're using
a system like Linker D the another kind
of factor to that is Linker D is able
to as part of this policy inforce is
actually doing it based on Mutual TLS
identity so you're moving away from
Reliance on IP tables and things like
that into cryptographic proof of
workload identity if you've got zero
trust mandates or whatever suddenly that
becomes very very interesting to you
because you can't really trust a network
and even in a system like kubernetes you
know when you get down to it the people
who are really sophisticated at security
there are ways where in the presence of
network partitions there are ways where
the IP tables based approaches that
Network policy to use actually can fail
can fail in kind of horrific ways for
security reasons where they allow
traffic that that they're not supposed
to allow so you get a baseline level
from Network policies but you kind of
need to extend that depending on your
requirements of course you need to
extend that into something like a
service mesh to get the next step that's
a great explanation of the difference
between the two and where I want to get
to is discussing kubernetes and side
cars I think it would make sense at this
point me to ask you in this history
where service smesh Concepts predated
kubernetes then on the other side of the
wall we have service mesh running on
kubernetes was there a
migration from of service mesh onto
kubernetes what did that look like well
there certainly was for us in in Linker
land and what that looked like was a big
old rewrite you know the thing you're
never supposed to do so we started out
you know and now this is diving into
ancient history but we started out with
linkerd 1.x was actually written you
know was based off of these very cool
very powerful libraries that had been
open sourced by Twitter which where we
had come out of just a year prior so it
was based on the jvm and it was written
in Scala and it could do all this crazy
stuff and it was this beautiful general
purpose system you know that could talk
to kubernetes and Mos and console and
Nomad and all that stuff but the problem
was it was on the jvm and like we
rapidly ran into 99% of the universe not
really wanting to add the jvm to their
stack if it wasn't already there so we
took a step back and we said okay let's
think about designing this the right way
from the ground up and at that point we
also decided to focus very heavily on
kubernetes because it seemed like that's
where most of the interest was in this
architecture so we ended up rewriting
stuff in kind of a two component system
so linkerd 2.x has a control plane it
has a data plane and we made that sep
operation very very explicit it hadn't
really been explicit before and the
control plane we wrote in go you know
which is kind of the lingua franka of
the kubernetes ecosystem and we have all
these libraries it makes it easy for us
to talk to the kubernetes API and so on
and then the data plane we did something
that I think was a little radical
certainly was Radical at the time now
it's a genius move in in retrospect
luckily which is we wrote the data plane
in Rust and this was Circ of 2018 rust
was the language had like just hit 1.0
and the networking ecosystem was like in
shamble not in shambles just very very
nent so we spent the next couple years
kind of investing in that networking
ecosystem building up the data plane and
fast forward today we have this really
really powerful we don't even call it a
proxy we call it a micro proxy because
it's so small really powerful micro
proxy that's very linkerd specific so
it's not a general purpose object but is
able to do kind of the heavy lifting and
we get all these nice benefits from rust
around security
and you know not having buffer overflow
exploits and and things like that so
that was the evolution was basically a
giant leap from one planet to the next
planet what are the major components of
linker D that you need to install or run
or otherwise provide into kubernetes in
order to have link or Des service mesh
on kubernetes it's just a control well
adjust okay it's a control plane and the
data plane and the control plane is like
pretty straightforward it's a bunch of
go processes that sit in a name space
and the data plane is a little more
complex because that's where you
actually use the sidecar containers so
the data plane is like the generic term
for zero to a million sidecar proxies
that you have sprinkled throughout your
your stack and and this is where the
service mesh gets a little scary I think
the first time you look at it because
what it comes down to is hey you're
going to be running 10,000 proxies on
your machine right and like if that's
the first statement that you hear you're
like oh boy that sounds crazy and then
we say well but don't worry you know
each one is in a container they're
really small they're go they're like
three Megs or something and you don't
have to and I think this is really
critical from the kind of operational
perspective you don't really have to
think about them directly these are not
proxies like you're used to thinking
about my Apache proxy that sits at the
front and handles all my traffic and is
you know requires tuning and an Apache
expert and all that stuff at least you
know maybe I'm showing my age that's how
things used to be these are just little
components that so off to to the side
and you know they don't require a lot of
configuration and it becomes a little
more manageable once you understand
exactly the nature of the data plane and
also the tools that kubernetes gives you
right I talked earlier about why the
service mesh and kubernetes are almost
always paired together it's because we
rely what kubernetes gives us is things
like the ability to add this proxy in a
really transparent way to every pod that
you spin up in your application without
you having to do a whole bunch of work
okay great and then to have that proxy
configured to talk to the control plane
and to have a little TLS certificate
Authority and to kind of build in and to
do the network wiring and run IP tables
automatically so that all traffic to and
from the Pod goes through the proxy
container all of that is doable pretty
much transparently to you the operator
because of The Primitives that
kubernetes provides and now in the next
version of linkerd which is coming out
in the next month or two so probably by
the time you hear this might be out
already 2.15 we are building this
feature called mesh expansion where you
can run the proxy outside of kubernetes
so we're kind of like coming in a full
circle now right so the control plane
though still has to stay on kubernetes
but the data plane the proxy can run
outside of kubernetes and now we're
having to reinvent a lot of those things
that we were relying on kubernetes 4
because now we're in the wild west of
like okay run this proxy on a VM what do
we know about this VM nothing what can
we rely on being there nothing right so
we kind of have to you know we're
finally back in this world of having to
support arbitrary environments time
permits I might come back to the last
thing you said but I wanted to dive in
to a list of things you said that
kubernetes helps you with one that stood
out was it enables these sidecars or
proxies to run on your pods
transparently without you having to
configure it on each and every pod what
kubernetes mechanism did you use to make
that happen yeah so we use something
called a with the Glorious name of a
mutating admission web hook controller
which basically means from the user
perspective you add an annotation that
says hey I would like this name space or
this workload or whatever to you know
all the pods in this workload or all the
pods in this name space to be enabled
with Linker and then when those pods get
created linkerd is able to insert the
yaml block effectively that says okay
and also add
the sidecar container which contains a
proxy oh and also add the init container
which sets up the wiring oh and also do
X Y and Z and so there is a component in
the control plane that basically
responds to these kubernetes API calls
where kubernetes is saying hey I'm
spinning up a pod here do you want to do
something to it and that component will
read see if that annotation is present
and if so it'll insert the corresponding
manifest to spin up the container and
the init container and everything else
as part of the pod initialization
sequence so then your perspective as a
user is oh I just add this annotation
and things magically work right which is
kind of cool yeah that is cool and one
other thing out of that list that stood
out to me was of course you need a CA
somewhere in there if you're doing mtls
how does the linkerd bootstrap the CA
and get the certificates to be issued to
the side cars yeah so I it's another
thing I've got a long and boring blog
post about but in effect you have
there's a little CA that runs as part of
the linkerd control plane and we just
call it the identity service and every
time a pod starts up let me see if I can
get this right the Pod itself issues a
at initialization time it's given the
trust anchors so this basically says
here's a public key of like your trust
chain right so that's public information
and that's static in the case of linker
D you know that's static for the
lifetime of the proxy so if you need to
change that you have to restart start
the you've got to restart the proxy and
then that the proxy on Startup it says
okay I'm going to issue a CSR
certificate signing request it sends
that to the control plane and the
control plane validates that the proxy
is who it says it is and then sends the
certificate back and those certificates
by default the lifetime is 24 hours you
could make them even smaller if you want
so you rotate those certificates pretty
rapidly you know which is kind of our
approach to handling the risk of like
losing a certificate and the identity in
that certificate is the identity
provided by the kubernetes service
account so in kubernetes your service
account is basically your identity as
far as security kind of goes so out of
the box you get this Mutual TLS system
that's all set up for you you don't have
to do any of that and the identity is
the workload identity so you've already
moved from like Network identity to
workload identity and then every time
you make a meshed call every time you
have a call from one pod to another
where they both have the linkerd proxy
that is automatically upgraded to Mutual
tills both proxies validate the identity
on the other side they apply whatever
policy they want based on identity and
then reject or accept the call as
necessary and so that kind of all
happens for you without you having to do
really any
configuration with one or two Aster
risks in that statement in my mind
that's kind of cool could you pick one
of these kubernetes integration features
and either give me an example of
something that you've seen go wrong in
uction or a story about a
troubleshooting experience you had in
one of these features okay that I'm
going to tell you a slightly
embarrassing story which is just because
it's it's top those are the best
kind well I don't know I don't know
maybe I shouldn't tell the story we were
having at some point we were having a
bunch of reports of like this really
weird behavior and one of the horrible
things about running an open- source
project is that you know it's other
people who are running this at scale and
in weird environments that you don't
always have access to and then they're
reporting these bugs and they might not
always be the best at like describing
what's happening or debugging a complex
system is an art you know and that art
rapidly breaks down when it's got a
barrier between you know different
people on different teams and different
time zones and different kind of
abilities to communicate but eventually
we were like ah wrapping our you know
trying to figure out what was going on
here was like oh is it kubernetes maybe
their kubernetes API is not scaling up
you know we were finding these issues
where there was a disconnect between
what Linker was seeing what the
kubernetes API was seeing and then
finally you know after after kind of
thinking for a while that maybe they
just were under provisioning the kuber
identities API we went back and we
combed through all the code and we
realized that in there in the control in
the linkerd control plane this is the
horrible part we were using like a
default Constructor in this one place
for the the client that talks to the
kubernetes AP and then we read through
the docs and then the docs were like oh
this client by default has a rate limit
of like five requests per second or
something you know which is pretty low
for us and so we realized that actually
we were rate limiting ourselves in
talking to the kubernetes API
unknowingly in this one part of the code
and when we fixed that you know
magically everything everything worked
so that's a embarrassing story of you
know how Linker D well and what's
embarrassing about it is like I think
how long it took us to figure out what
was going on cuz you have to start from
these very weird descriptions they
manifest in all sorts of crazy oh I'm
seeing this error message in this one
thing and it says something about http2
upgrades and you're like okay you have
to somehow Trace that all the way back
to oh I've got a there's a default rate
limit in our in our API toet yeah well
most problems are pretty simple once you
solve them yes right yeah in retrospect
ah trivial one line fix okay William
where I want to get to in a few minutes
is this k753 the proposal for side cars
on kubernetes but prior to this proposal
was it possible to run sidecars in
kubernetes and what kind of issues did
you run into oh yeah we've been running
side cars in kubernetes since 2018 maybe
even earlier 2017 there's one or two
warts or there always have been one or
two warts around that because kubernetes
up until this K had no notion of a
sidecar container so you know we would
call it a sidecar but from Net's point
of view it's just some other container
running in the Pod I'm going to stop you
there because I realized it's another
question I think it would make sense ask
you first which is sure in kubernetes so
pod can have multiple containers you
explain what is the life cycle of a pod
including all the different containers
and when they
run yeah well so the life cycle a pod is
actually pretty complicated and you know
you can find a diagram of this thing out
in the docks and it's non-trivial at the
macro level there's kind of at least
prior to this K there's only two types
of containers there's init containers
and then there's regular containers and
the init containers the only thing
you're guaranteed is that they will run
before the regular containers run and
they're expected to terminate and then
regular containers they start after the
init containers but they run forever
until they're forced to to terminate and
those are kind of the only guarantees
that you have again prior to the this
this k
so that's all well and good although it
has a couple implications one of them is
that from kubernetes perspective there's
nothing special about the Linker D
sidecar container it's just one
container of the between one to Infinity
containers in the Pod right and so that
all worked fine except in in a couple
cases and this is where like you start
seeing these little warts one big wart
was around jobs so jobs are a type of
workload in kubernetes where the regular
container terminates at the end so you
know it does its work and then it stops
you know in contrast to like a service
that's expected to run Forever Until
killed well that was all fine except the
linkerd side car container would keep
running and therefore kubernetes would
never clean up this pot it would never
terminate it and there was no mechanism
in there to clean it up right there's no
mechanism to signal to the sidecar to
linkerd that hey this pod's done shut
down and and move on so you had to do
these kind of not ideal workarounds
where you'd have like a tie in from the
application to the the proxy where you'd
have to like you'd have to Signal it
you'd have to say hey I'm done now proxy
you can terminate yeah so it's not the
end of the world but it kind of it's a
little gross because now you don't have
this really nice isolation between the
application container and the proxy and
you could do it in in the docker
manifest you could you know and we gave
you these utilities that would make it
really easy but still it was it was just
kind of like impure that was one of the
warts with prior to this KP that's
probably the biggest one were there any
others there were some other ones around
I think ordering of init containers so
sometimes so the way linkerd works is
before the proxy runs it runs in a knit
container that basically does the IP
tables networking and until that you
know until that runs the proxy itself
can't run but there's a a race there
were occasionally race conditions where
you'd have other things running as a
knit containers that expected the
network to be up or that expected to
talk through the prox
okay that was a little gross you know
and at some point we had to do a hack
and now I'm forgetting the details where
we had the proxy be the first container
you know so containers ordinary
containers there's like the first one
the second one it really only matters
for like what's the default output but
that actually fixed
something around a race condition with
like expecting the proxy to run and like
you know you just had like a a series of
little hacks like that but when the
proxy is the first container then by
default when you ask kubernetes for the
logs of a pod it gives you the proxy
logs instead your application logs well
okay so now we have to like rewrite all
of our commands to like talk about the
second container not the first container
it's just a series of little weirdnesses
like that you mentioned you've been
following closely if not contributing to
the K I don't know if you can think of
it completely fresh but did you have an
idea of how you wish it would work or
how you think it should work in the
ideal world what would kuber have to do
to make side cars work the way they
should I don't think I had a specific
implementation in mind I just had a
strong desire to like fix some of these
warts on behalf of our users and and
I'll say I have a lot of appreciation
for the fact that this is not a trivial
problem what we're asking or what the K
was asking and part of the reason why
this is interesting is because this K
like was kicked off in 2019 you know so
it's that's it's been around for a while
and there's been fits and starts
and I think some of the early approaches
quickly got very very complex right
because you don't want to have an
arbitrary you know you've already got
this complicated life cycle for pods
within a pod you don't want to have some
super complicated mechanism for the
containers and you don't want to end up
with like an arbitrary directed de
cyclic graph of like dependencies or
whatever in there so you kind of have to
find the right balance there so no I
didn't have an implementation in mind
but I did have a strong desire and like
I said in the very beginning my
involvement in this case is just
Cheerleading from the side I didn't
solve any problems I didn't do any hard
work I just like clapped my hands and
and wrote a blog post at the end we've
mentioned k a bunch of times do you have
knowledge of first what does k stand for
stand for kubernetes enhancement
proposal do you have knowledge of how
these KS what is the life cycle of a k
you know I'm definitely not the best
person to ask for that they you propose
them a bunch of complicated stuff
happens a bunch of really smart people
you know get involved and then at the
end code gets written or not that's my
knowledge of the life cycle fair enough
let's talk then about
k753 what is the title or the main
fraction of that K it's known
anecdotally I think as a sidecar K you
know and I think that the official title
is like sidecar containers or something
you know very tur like that but yeah it
was picked off in January of 2019 so
gosh almost what was that almost 5 years
ago with the idea being that hey there
are all these systems that have sidecars
but they have these warts around jobs
and whatever else and so kubernetes
should do a better job of supporting
that especially since in the kubernetes
docs themselves it says oh and sidec car
containers are like a cool pattern you
can use with kubernetes so the next five
years were kind of like if you read
through the history a series of fits and
starts of people trying to figure out
okay how do we tackle this in a way that
doesn't totally blow up into an
arbitrary container life cycle
management system what are the changes
contained in
753 yeah so at the kind of the final
resolution here was that we do have a
type of sidecar container right we we
now have for the first time kubernetes
you know a kubernetes object that's a
side car well it doesn't actually say
sidecar in it but it is a you know it's
almost like a background container mode
for init containers so what this K
introduces is a flag that you can set on
an knit container that you know which
and the flag is like a little obtuse you
know but it makes sense once you
understand the details it's like restart
policy always right and if you set that
flag on there that init container is now
basically a sidecar container and what
you're guaranteed is because it's an
init container container it starts
before all your regular containers just
like before but it now terminates after
all the ordinary containers terminate so
that's a new feature right so if you're
a job and your your regular container
terminates because the job's done you
are now guaranteed that your sidecar
container will terminate as well the
other interesting thing is that unlike
with normal and knit containers which
start in sequence so the first init
container starts then when it's done
remember in containers are expected to
terminate then the second init container
starts then it's done the sidecar mode
init containers don't wait for the other
innit containers to terminate that means
they can start ahead of time they can
get the network in shape which is what
the linkerd innit container does and any
other init containers that kind of rely
on that being there can Now operate so
that solves another class of problems
and if the side card if the side
container dies at any point while the
regular containers are running it gets
restart started automatically right so
that's kind of the why it was called
restart policy
always in reality it configures you know
setting something to restart policy
always changes a bunch of behaviors not
just a restart policy but that's how you
signal to kubernetes with a new K that's
how you signal that this is a sidecar
container so in one fell swop we solve
the jobs problem and we solve a bunch of
other kind of warts around sidecar usage
in
kubernetes the termination solves the
problem you mentioned earlier where the
main odd would have have to do some kind
of weird thing like a signal to get the
side car to stop is that correct yeah
that's right that's right my
understanding of kubernetes is in
control plane it has a lot of ways to
ensure you have the right amount of PODS
running but prior to this within a pod
you're pretty much on your own you had
multiple containers and one of them
failed well that's really your problem
this is something different do I
understand that correctly yeah I think
that's right it will now restart if you
Market this restart policy always it'll
restart this container while the other
containers are as long as the other
containers are running are you aware of
what is the it that is restarting the
sidecar container that's still the
kubernetes control plane and you
mentioned the interface to the dev is
they need to set a single field with the
value that you described and that's it
yeah that's right and that's really the
interface to the service mesh Dev that's
how linkerd triggers this Behavior you
as the operator as the user of the
sidecar or the operator of the
kubernetes cluster you don't need to set
that yourself because this is something
that'll be set by again by that mutating
admission web hook controller that
Linker is running in the control plane
that sets all the behavior and specifies
a manifest of the init container and of
the proxy container are there any
changes manifest in the kubernetes
command line I don't believe so I think
the beauty of this solution is that the
only kind of user facing like config
change is this new Option that's
available for specifying container you
know Behavior within a pod so everything
else Remains the Same when will this has
the K been implemented in the vernet's
source and when will it be merged into
General
availability yeah I believe that in one.
29 it will be in beta it was in Alpha
and 1.28 which meant 1.28 you could run
it but you would have to explicitly
enable it when you provisioned your
kubernetes cluster 1.28 is now in beta
and as of very recently linkerd itself
now supports this mode thanks to a
contribution from the community so 1.29
I think is where we'll start seeing this
in practice in the Linker world was the
main driver for this KP coming from the
service mesh Community or are there
other developers who have been wanting
to have a sidecar type functionality in
kubernetes that's a great question my
sense I may not be comprehensive I may
not have a comprehensive view but my
sense is the people who suffered the
most you know and I use suffering in
like the loosest sense possible given
real world events that are happen out
there people who suffered from not
having this were service mesh users
because that's I think the heaviest use
of side cars and that's also the one
that where we really push the boundaries
of sidecar containers is there anything
in these various threads that we've
covered that you wanted to add on that
we haven't discussed I think the only
thing if I were to summarize this I
think from my you know and I can give my
perspective as a linkerd not even
maintainer at this point maybe I
maintain the read me file right like
linky proponent which is I think in my
mind one of the most powerful things
that kubernetes has brought to the table
is this sidecar model I think it's a
really really effective way of in
practice
giving two teams that kind of have a
different set of priorities it's a
platform owner team and the developer
team the ability to merge their
functionality without incurring kind of
unnecessary dependency so we've had
these warts for a while and it's awesome
to see them get ironed out and
when I think about the future of linker
everything about the sidecar model still
really resonates with us there's other
options out there today but when you
look at kind of the solution space and
kind of the implications for security as
well as operations as well as visibility
it all keeps coming back to sidecars so
I guess I'll just say I'm happy we can
remove some of these warts and and
continue down this really really
powerful model that has been so
effective for so many Linker adopters
out there we will'll Link in the show
notes to as many blog posts as you'd
like that we've talked about during the
hour before we wrap up where can people
find you yeah so you can always find me
on slack. liner. come join me there and
say hi or you can always find me at
buoyant doio that's buo y n t that's a
company behind linkerd we build an
Enterprise version We invest heavily in
the open source we've got all sorts of
really cool stuff that we're doing on
top of linkerd so please come say hi
tell me that you found me through
software engineering radio yeah I would
love to talk to to anyone who's
interested William thank you very much
for speaking to software engineering
radio thanks for having me Robert it was
great to be here this has Ben Robert
bluman for software engineering radio
thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]
listening